原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/4g796kiGDyU
原视频发布日期：20200609
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
你好 我是Scott Manley
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
没人嫌马一龙画过的饼还不够多
Nobody can accuse Elon Musk of not talking about big ideas for the future
而这些年来 我们已经看到和听到了许多SpaceX火箭的消息
and over the years we've seen and heard about a number of SpaceX rockets
那种先发布出来 后来随着公司商业模式的发展而被砍了
which were announced and then later failed by the wayside as the company's business model evolved
所以我想 回去看看这些方案是很有意思的
and so I thought it would be interesting to go back and look at the rockets
它们曾是SpaceX公司合理的下一步方案 但一直也没能上天
which were once the logical next step for SpaceX but never made it to flight
当然 我们首先要谈的是猎鹰1号相关的话题
and of course the place that we have to start is with the Falcon 1.
而早在SpaceX开始的时候 它只被称为猎鹰号
And back when SpaceX started it was only known as the Falcon
指千年隼(Millennium Falcon)
而它的名字当然是以星球大战的某个传奇飞船命名的
and it was named of course after a certain legendary Star Wars spacecraft.
那么来看看猎鹰 其一级使用了一台梅林一号发动机
Now for reference the Falcon used a single Merlin one engine for the first stage
其二级采用了挤压循环的红隼发动机
and a pressure fed Kestrel engine for the second stage.
火箭高约22米 加满燃料后质量为30t
The rocket was roughly 22 metres tall and massed 30 tons fully fuelled.
早期的猎鹰使用的是梅林1A发动机 它的燃烧室和喷嘴都是烧蚀冷却的
The early Falcons used the Merlin 1A which had an ablative nozzle and combustion chamber
但后来的飞行中 他们使用了改进的Merlin 1C 其使用再生冷却 并有着更高的推力
but later flights they used the improved Merlin 1C with regenerative cooling and higher thrusts.
根据SpaceX早期的公告
According to SpaceX is early announcements,
猎鹰号将能够以600万美元的价格将一个600kg的有效载荷发射到轨道上
the Falcon would be able to launch a six hundred kilogram payload into orbit for a price of six million dollars
但到了实际飞行时 已经改为400kg的有效载荷 而价格为900万美元
but by the time it was actually flying this had changed to four hundred kilogram payloads for nine million dollars.
猎鹰1号的五次飞行都是从南太平洋的夸贾林环礁进行的
The five flights of the Falcon 1 were all carried out from the Kwajalein Atoll in the South Pacific.
但早在猎鹰1号飞行之前 SpaceX就已经开始谈论升级版
But long before the Falcon 1 ever flew, SpaceX was already talking about upgraded versions.
2003年 SpaceX表示 重型猎鹰将是猎鹰的下一个改进版
in 2003 SpaceX said that the Falcon Heavy would be the next evolution of the Falcon
但这不是我们熟悉和喜爱的重型猎鹰
but this is not the Falcon Heavy we knew and loved.
这是三枚猎鹰1号芯级捆绑在一起 再加上猎鹰1号的上面级
This was three Falcon 1 core strapped together with a single Falcon 1 upper stage.
它将有能力把1.4t的东西送入近地轨道
This would have the ability to put 1.4 tons into low-earth orbit.
那会肖特韦尔还是她前夫的姓
汉斯则是现在SpaceX任务保障副总裁
这个概念出现在早期的SpaceX公关材料中 以及一个马一龙 汉斯 肖特韦尔联合署名的文件
The concept appears in early SpaceX PR material and in a paper by Elon, Hans and Gwynne.
但重型猎鹰的计划很快就被放弃了
But the plan for the Falcon Heavy was dropped soon
在SpaceX开始宣布多引擎版本的猎鹰之后
after SpaceX started announcing multi engine versions of the Falcon.
于是猎鹰就变成了猎鹰1号
So the Falcon became the Falcon 1.
在2003年的新闻发布会上 公布了第一款多引擎猎鹰概念
The first multi-engine Falcon concept was announced at a press conference in 2003
在那里他们展示了第一台猎鹰1号
where they had the first Falcon 1 on show.
我相信你一定能猜到 猎鹰5号第一级有五个梅林发动机
I'm sure you can guess that the Falcon 5 had five Merlin engines in the first stage.
第二级有两个红隼发动机
It had two Kestrel engines in the second stage.
现在火箭的直径将达到3.7m 也就是现在猎鹰的直径
The rocket would now be three point seven meters diameter which is the diameter of the current Falcons.
它将高29m 发射时约130t
It would be twenty nine metres tall and about a hundred and thirty tons at launch.
这将能把4t的重量送到低地球轨道上
This would be aimed at delivering four tons to low Earth orbit.
而马一龙实际上提议 这个火箭将能够向国际空间站运送货物
And Elon actually suggested that we'd be able to deliver cargo to the International Space Station.
它还能将卫星送入地球静止轨道
It would also have the capability of delivering satellites to geostationary orbit
并预计每次发射的成本为1200万美元
and had a projected cost of twelve million dollars per launch.
他还谈到了猎鹰5号的升级版 他们将使用更强大的梅林发动机
He also talked about an upgraded version of Falcon 5 where they would use more powerful Merlin engines.
这将使他们能够拉长一级储罐
It would allow them to stretch the booster tanks
二级将转向使用液氢 由RL-10发动机提供动力
and the second stage would move over to using liquid hydrogen powered by an RL-10 engine.
虽然这听起来很不错
And while that sounds great,
但我很确定RL-10发动机的成本会比火箭的剩余部分加在一起还要高
I'm pretty sure the RL-10 engine would have cost more than the rest of the rocket put together.
随着时间的推移 猎鹰5号有些变化
The Falcon 5 morphed somewhat over time.
发动机进行了升级
The engines were upgraded.
二级换成了使用单台梅林发动机 并延长了喷管
the second stage was switched to use a single Merlin engine with a nozzle extension.
而在2005年 猎鹰9号被公布
And in 2005 the Falcon 9 was announced
我们都知道这就是他们最终选择的未来 这就是现在发生的事情
and we all know that this is the future that they ultimately went with and that's what happened
但猎鹰5并没有马上被放弃
but the Falcon 5 didn't get abandoned right away.
任何重大的重新设计都旨在消除制造过程中的冗余
Any major redesign aimed removing redundancy from the manufacturing process.
猎鹰5号改用与猎鹰9号相同的助推箱 但只有五个发动机
The Falcon 5 switched to using the same booster tanks as the Falcon 9 but with only five engines.
本质上是去掉了四个发动机的猎鹰9号
Essentially a Falcon 9 with four engines removed.
而且储罐只会加注一部分燃料 这样发动机就能推动它
And the tanks would only be partially filled so that the engines could lift it.
发射成本就会因此上升 有效载荷质量下降
The cost of flight then rose as a result and the payload mass dropped.
同时后面还有一个叫猎鹰9号S5的东西
At the same time late there was something called the Falcon 9S5
这就像新版的重型猎鹰 但绑上了猎鹰5号助推器
which was like the modern Falcon heavy but with Falcon 5 boosters strapped on.
这与9S9同时公布的
This was announced in parallel with the 9S9.
9S9的概念(比S5)更类似新版的重型猎鹰
The concept which is much more like the modern Falcon Heavy.
而这也就是我们以前看到的猎鹰5的最后一个化身
And that was the last incarnation of the Falcon 5 that we saw
在这之后2007年的SpaceX文件中它就消失了
before it disappeared from SpaceX documents in 2007.
与此同时 猎鹰1号的计划还在继续 他们实际上也在进行测试发射
At the same time the Falcon 1 program was continuing and they were actually having test launches.
早期的猎鹰1号确实遇到了很多梅林发动机的问题
They did have a lot of problems in the early days with the Merlin engine
然后火箭也出现了一系列的问题
and then they had a series of problems with rockets
但他们试图继续向客户推销猎鹰1号
but they continued trying to sell the Falcon 1 to customers
于是他们公布了猎鹰1E
and so they announced the Falcon 1E.
猎鹰1E将猎鹰的结构改造为重量更轻的铝锂合金
The Falcon 1E converted the structure of the Falcon to a lighter weight aluminium lithium alloy.
它拉长了储罐 而且它的有效载荷整流罩更大
It stretched the tanks and it had a larger payload fairing.
使火箭的长度增加了约5米 质量提高到接近40t左右
Adding about five more meters to the rocket and raising the mass closer to about 40 tons.
梅林1C发动机及其再生冷却燃烧室
The Merlin 1C engine with his new fancy regeneratively cooled combustion chamber
能够多提供30%的推力
was able to deliver 30 percent more thrust.
而SpaceX表示猎鹰1E将以1100万美元的价格将1t的重量送入近地轨道
And SpaceX said that the Falcon 1E would put one ton into low-earth orbit for the sum of 11 million dollars.
首次发射计划在2010年进行
The first flight was scheduled for 2010
但随着NASA的商业载人开发计划为猎鹰9号带来了真金白银
but with NASA's Commercial Crew development bringing in the real money for Falcon 9,
猎鹰1E的开发被暂停了 因为SpaceX把所有的精力都放在让NASA满意上面
the Falcon 1E development was suspended as SpaceX put all its effort into making NASA happy.
最重要的是 经济危机扼杀了很多潜在的小卫星客户
On top of this the economic crash killed a lot of potential small sat customers
所以SpaceX并没有因为搁猎鹰1E而丢掉了很多收益
so SpaceX weren't turning down massive profits by shelving Falcon 1E.
终于在2012年 SpaceX宣布
Finally in 2012, SpaceX announced that
比如福卫五号
猎鹰1E的有效载荷都被转移到猎鹰9号上 作为次要的有效载荷
the payloads that had been booked for the Falcon 1E were all shifted over to the Falcon 9 as secondary payloads.
最后被放弃的猎鹰概念是猎鹰9号Air版
The final abandoned Falcon concept was the Falcon 9 Air.
它是2011年开始与平流层发射系统合作的一部分
which was part of a collaboration with Stratolaunch that began in 2011.
这个概念指空射版的猎鹰9号
the concept was an air launched version of the Falcon 9
它将与庞大的平流层发射系统运载飞机合作
which would work with the massive Stratolaunch carrier aircraft.
尽管被命名为猎鹰9号 但它的一级只有四个发动机
Despite being named Falcon 9 it only had four engines in the first stage
更加令人困惑的是 早期的概念视频显示它有五个发动机
and to add to the confusion the early concept video showed it with five engines.
在平流层发射系统飞机的帮助下 它也许能把6t重的东西送入轨道
With the help of the Stratolaunch aircraft it could have been able to put maybe six tons into orbit.
因为它将是空中发射 猎鹰Air版会有一个由缩尺复合公司生产的机翼
Because it would be air launched, the Falcon air included a wing which would be built by Scaled Composites.
随着时间的推移 设计的演变意味着对火箭的定制程度要求越来越高
And over time the design evolution meant that more and more specialization of the rocket was required
这使它与老式的地面发射版本有所不同
which differentiated it from the old-fashioned ground launch version.
其所需的结构性载荷主要是通过将加满燃料的火箭侧挂在飞机上产生的
Primarily the structural loads which were required are generated by hanging a fully fueled rocket sideways in a plane
与垂直站在发射台上的火箭的结构载荷完全不同
are radically different from the structural loads on a rocket standing vertically in the launch pad.
所以 这意味着猎鹰9号和猎鹰9号Air版之间的相同度消失了不少
So that meant that the degree of commonality between the Falcon 9 and the Falcon 9 Air disappeared
也就意味着会比SpaceX最初想象的更不经济
which meant there was less economical than SpaceX had originally imagined.
所以最终SpaceX决定不再走这条路线了
So eventually SpaceX decided that it was no longer the route that it wanted to pursue
他们退出了平流层发射系统
and they dropped out of Stratolaunch,
让猎鹰9号Air版停留在图纸上
leaving the Falcon 9 Air on the drawing board.
最后 我想我们还应该提到
Finally I guess we should also mention that
最初还有一个使用猎鹰9号1.0的重型猎鹰被推销过
there was a version of the Falcon Heavy originally pitched that used the Falcon 9 1.0.
猎鹰9号1.0当然没有八个一圈的排列方式
The Falcon 9 1.0 of course didn't have the Octaweb engine arrangement.
而是排列在一个网格中 而且它的长度也短了很多
It had them arranged in a grid and it was a whole lot shorter
所以重型猎鹰的原始渲染图就是这种设计
so the original renderings of the Falcon Heavy are of this design.
很明显 这种重型猎鹰没被制造出来过 因为重型猎鹰改为使用更大的猎鹰9号1.1版
Clearly that was never built largely because they had moved over to the larger Falcon 9 1.1
所以这就是最初的或者说第二版的重型猎鹰火箭从未飞过的原因
and so that's why the original or the second version the Falcon Heavy never flew.
所以啊 这些都是SpaceX从未制造过的猎鹰火箭
So yeah those are the Falcon rockets that SpaceX never built.
计划被制定了 数字被计算了 渲染图也有了
Plans were made. Numbers were crunched. Renderings happened.
但这些火箭都没有真正飞起来
But none of these actually flew.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.